David Murray Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
David Murray Papers 1866-1930 1873-1879
MSS33985
Murray, David, 1830-1905
250 items
5 containers
2 linear feet
3 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Educator. Mainly writings and notes by Murray on education and the history and culture of Japan based on Murray’s observations while superintending the educational reform of that country.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Murray family--Correspondence.; Murray, David, 1830-1905.; Murray, Martha A.--Correspondence.
Subjects
Arts--Japan.; Education--Japan.; Education--United States.; Educational change.; Ethnology--Japan.; Indians of North America.; Lotteries.; Wampum.
Places
Japan--Description and travel.; Japan--History.; Japan--Politics and government.; Japan--Social conditions.
Occupations
Educators.
Acquisition Information
The papers of David Murray, educator, apparently came to the Library of Congress in two installments. Nearly a hundred manuscripts of Murray’s lectures, articles, and notes were given by his widow, Martha Neilson Murray, circa 1915. Hamilton Fish Armstrong, editor of Foreign Affairs and a cousin of Mrs. Murray, gave additional material in 1946.
Access and Restrictions
The David Murray Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on three reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1830, Oct. 15 Born, Bovina, N.Y.
1852 Graduated, Union College, Schenectady. N.Y.
1857 1863 Principal, Albany Academy, Albany, N.Y.
1863 Ph.D., University of New York
1863 1873 Professor of mathematics, Rutgers College, New Brunswick, N.J.
1867 Married Martha A. Neilson
1873 1879 Superintendent of educational affairs, Japan
1880 1889 Secretary, Board of Regents, University of New York
1892 1905 Member and secretary, Board of Trustees, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, N.J.
1894 Published The Story of Japan. New York: G. P. Putnam’s Sons
1899 Published History of Education in New Jersey. Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office
1905, Mar. 6 Died, New Brunswick, N.J.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of David Murray (1830-1905) span the years 1866-1930, with the bulk of the material in the period 1873-1879. The collection contains notes on education, government, history, art, social conditions, and ethnology in Japan made while Murray was superintending the educational reform of the country. It also contains addresses and scholarly papers based on the notes; letters written from Japan by David or his wife, Martha A. Nielson Murray, to relatives in the United States; and addresses and papers on education in the United States, Native American wampum, lotteries, and other subjects.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized by type of material.
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 18.047
- Personal papers (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Family correspondence, 1873-1879, (7 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Invitations received, 1873-1878 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Genealogies, undated (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Contract with and commission from the Japanese government, 1873-1875 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - W. I. Chamberlain, In Memoriam: David Murray, Ph.D., LL.D., 1915 (Box 1, Reel 1)
- Papers and addresses upon Japan (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Lists of papers and addresses in collection, undated (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Notes (Box 2, Reel 1)
    - circa 1877-circa 1878 (Box 2, Reel 1)
    - circa 1878, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Drafts of The Story of Japan, circa 1892 (Box 2, Reel 2)
    - Chapter XIII (Box 2, Reel 2)
    - Chapter XIV (Box 2, Reel 2)
    - Chapter XV (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Other drafts (Box 3, Reel 2)
    - 1875-circa 1880 (Box 3, Reel 2)
    - circa 1895-1904 (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - Addresses and lecture, 1873-circa 1880 (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - Lectures (Box 3, Reel 2)
    - circa 1880 (Box 3, Reel 2)
    - 1897-circa 1900 (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - Reports, 1877-1878 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Other writings, circa 1876-circa 1892 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Miscellany, 1878-1879 (Box 4, Reel 3)
- Papers and addresses in America (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Notes upon lotteries, 1890-1893 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Addresses, circa 1866-1885 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Address as honorary chancellor of Union College, Schenectady, N.Y., 1885 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Lecture upon lotteries, 1890 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Addresses, 1895-1901 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Lectures upon wampum, 1900-1902 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Other writings, 1882-1896 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - Labels and portion of newspaper, 1930, undated (Box 4, Reel 3)